Ricardo Camacho Castilla

(+61) 0404 721 837
East Melbourne, Australia
rcamachocast@student.unimelb.edu.au

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I am a civil and environmental engineer with a Master's in Civil Engineering for Risk Mitigation from Politecnico di Milano. Currently, I am a PhD Candidate at the University of Melbourne. My research focuses on the relationship between urban planning and disaster risk reduction, studying human settlement risk, sustainability, and dynamics before and after a disastrous event through spatial analysis and remote sensing. I am a researcher at the Centre for Disaster Management and Public Safety (CDMPS), the Centre for Spatial Data Infrastructures and Land Administration (CSDILA), and the Research Group in EO and AI. I am proactive and methodic, have strong analytic and leadership skills, and have excellent teamwork capabilities.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Tutor, The University of Melbourne, Parkville (AUS) – (Jul 2022 – Present)

 Assisted the lecturer on the subject of Digital Infrastructure Systems Capstone (previously Integrated Spatial Systems) (GEOM30012), tutoring students, demonstrating laboratory equipment, and grading assignments.

Instructor professor (Full-time Young Lecturer), University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) - (Jan 2017 - Jan 2020)

- Leader of the Geomatics area in the Civil and Environmental Engineering Department.
- I supervised six undergraduate and four graduate research theses. Four of these were published in international congresses.
- Co-convened, alongside NASA and Water Youth Network, the international event Hack the Risk Smart Solutions on Water Issues and Floods in April 2019.

Researcher, University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) - (Jan 2017 - Dec 2020)

- Developed a cellular automata-based land use cover change model for the city of Cali (Colombia) and its metropolitan region.
- Created a population density model for the City of Bogota adding a third dimension to a land use cover change model using a machine learning-based approach.
- Studied the 2017 mudslides in Mocoa, Colombia and its consequences from past urban misguided developing in the city, resulting in one
 award, one publication in a peer reviewed journal, and multiple presentations.
- Developed local mass movement mitigation strategies with the town of Las Mesas' community settled in the skirts of an active volcano in southwest Colombia.
- Analysed the density of invasive species, forest regeneration, and macrophytes growth using multispectral imagery, UAVs, and analysis of historical documents and data, in three different National Natural Parks of Colombia.
- Six research articles were published in ISI Q1 journals. Oral and poster publications in over ten conferences and congresses.
- Member of the research group on Urban and Regional Sustainability (SUR).
- Member of the Research Portfolio on Historical Ecology and Social Memory (EHMS).
- Member of the DRR Working Group of the United Nations Major Group for Children and Youth (UNMGCY).

EDUCATION

PhD in Engineering & IT

The University of Melbourne, Parkville (AUS) – (Dec 2020 – Present)

Thesis: "Spatial dynamics of the informal urban growth in disaster-prone cities: impact on resilience and sustainability practices."

Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Jagannath Aryal | Prof. Abbas Rajabifard

MSc in Civil Engineering for Risk Mitigation

Politecnico di Milano, Lecco (ITA) – (Sep 2014 – Dec 2016)

Thesis: "Enhancing structured and organised post-disaster damage loss data according to the SFDRR. Case: June 2013 flooding in Vall d'Aran and the Pyrenees" Advisor: Prof. Scira Menoni | Dr Ouejdane Mejri

Bachelor in Environmental Engineering

University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) – (Aug 2010 – Oct 2014)

Bachelor in Civil Engineering

University of Los Andes, Bogota (COL) - (Jan 2010 - Mar 2014)

EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

Cooking, woodworking, gardening, sailing.

SKILLS

- Languages:
- Computer skills:

Spanish: Native speaker – English: Full proficiency – Italian: A2 level.

PUBLICATIONS

- **R. Camacho**, J. Aryal, and A. Rajabifard, "Disaster-induced disruption of policies for informal urban settlements.", *Cities* (2024). DOI: 10.1016/j.cities.2024.105098
- N. Pardo, R. Sulpizio, F. Lucchi, G. Giordano, S. Cronin, B. Pulgarin, M. Roverato, A. M. Correa, R. Camacho, and M. Cabrera, "Late Holocene volcanic stratigraphy and eruption chronology of the dacitic Young Doña Juana volcano, Colombia.", GSA Bulletin (2023). DOI: 10.1130/B36557.1
- S. Salazar, R. Camacho, S. Villota, N. Pardo, A. Velasquez, M. Cabrera and, B. Pulgarin, "Geomorphology on a tropical volcanic setting: interplay of fluvial, gravitational, structural, and volcanic processes in the Doña Juana Volcanic Complex, Colombia.", Journal of Maps (2022). DOI: 10.1080/17445647.2022.2101948
- L.A. Guzman, **R. Camacho**, D.A. Rodriguez, and C. Beltrán, "Modeling population density guided by land use cover change model: a case study of Bogotá", *Population and Environment* (2022). DOI: 10.1007/s11111-022-00400-5
- N. Pardo, C. Gonzalez, M. Espinosa, M. Cabrera, S. Salazar, S. Archila, N. Palacios, D. Prieto, R. Camacho, and L. Parra, "Worlding resilience in the Doña Juana Volcano, Northern Andes (Colombia): a transdisciplinary view", Natural Hazards (2021). DOI: 10.1007/s11069-021-04662-4
- L. Navarro, R. Camacho, J. Gallego, and J.F. Saldarriaga, "Assessment of the potential risk of leaching pesticides in agricultural soils: Study case Tibasosa, Boyaca, Colombia", Heliyon (2021). DOI: 10.1016/J.HELIYON.2021.E08301
- L.F. Prada-Sarmiento, M. Cabrera, R. Camacho, N. Estrada, and A. Ramos, "The Mocoa Event on March 31 (2017). Analysis of a series of
 mass movements in a tropical environment of the Andean-Amazonian Piedmont.", Landslides (2019). DOI: 10.1007/s10346-019-01263-y

POSTER AND ORAL PRESENTATIONS

- R. Camacho, A. Rajabifard, and J. Aryal, "Do disasters disrupt the spatial growth of informal settlements? The case of Mocoa, Colombia",
 Oral at the 42nd EARSeL Symposium, Manchester, UK. 17 20 Jun, 2024.
- R. Camacho, A. Rajabifard, and J. Aryal, "Spatial growth patterns of informal settlements in disaster environments: The case of Mocoa, Colombia", Oral at the LOCATE23, Adelaide, Australia. 10 12 May, 2023.
- R. Camacho, A. Rajabifard, and J. Aryal, "Disaster induced disruption of Informal Urban Settlements and spatial growth patterns: Three case studies in Latin-America", Oral at the International Symposium on Rebuilding Communities after Displacement, Online. 13 14 Dic, 2021.
- L.A. Guzman, R. Camacho, and A. Rodriguez, "Análisis espacio-temporal de los viajes en patinetas en Bogotá", Oral at the XXI PANAM 2021, Online. 11 13 Ago, 2021.
- L.A. Guzman, R. Camacho, C. Beltran, and A. Rodriguez, "The 3D component of a land-use change model for Bogotá: A random forest-based population density model", Oral at the XXI PANAM 2021, Online. 11 13 Aug, 2021.
- N. Pardo, M. Cabrera, C. Gonzalez, M. Espinosa, R. Camacho, N. Palacios, S. Salazar, L. Parra, and S. Archila, "A transdisciplinary approach to mass-movements mitigation strategies in volcanic habitats: an approach from complex systems", Oral at the EGU General Assembly 2020, Online. 4 8 May, 2020.
- M. Cabrera, L.F. Prada-Sarmiento, R. Camacho, N. Estrada, and A. Ramos, "The Mocoa 2017 Event. A case-study of mass movements in the Andean-Amazonian Piedmont", Poster at the AGU Fall Meeting 2019, San Francisco, USA. 9 13 Dec, 2019.
- J.R. Escorcia, R. Camacho, and J. Wills, "Historical analysis of road infrastructure accessibility in Colombia," Oral at the FIG Working Week 2019, Hanoi, Vietnam. 22 29 Apr, 2019.
- L. Cardenas, C. Salcedo, and R. Camacho, "Comparison of two methodologies to estimate flood footprints based in GIS using hydrological data", Oral at the International Perspectives on Water and the Environment IPWE2018, Cartagena, Colombia. 04 07 Dec, 2018.
- S. Rodriguez, D. Paez, and R. Camacho, "Analysis of the multipurpose cadastre use for risk and disaster management in Colombia", Oral at the 26th FIG International Congress 2018, Istanbul, Turkey. 06 11 May, 2018.
- R. Camacho, and D. Paez, "Agricultural Border Displacement as a Consequence of Climate Change. Case: Coffee in Colombia", Oral at the 16th Annual World Bank Conference on Land and Poverty, Washington DC, USA. 23 27 Mar, 2015.

SCHOLARSHIPS AND AWARDS

- Nov 2022 Dejar Huella recognition. Best Impactful Project. Awarded by Universidad de Los Andes.
- Sep 2021 Biennial Javeriana Award in Research. Awarded by Pontificia Universidad Javeriana.
- Dec 2020 Partial fee remission Graduate Research Scholarship. Awarded by The University of Melbourne.
- Jan 2020 Beneficiary of the Call of Proposals 860 of 2019 to undertake doctoral studies abroad. Awarded by the Ministry of Science, Technology, and Innovation of Colombia.
- Jun 2019 Innovative Professor Award. Awarded by Universidad de Los Andes.
- Oct 2018 80% Scholarship in Technical Formation in Woodworking, Funded by Santo Domingo Foundation.
- Sep 2014 UniverLecco Gold Scholarship. Merit scholarship for international students. Awarded by UniverLecco Foundation